David Swayne

Chief Information Officer at Goldsmiths, University of London

d.swayne@btinternet.com

Summary

A P&L experienced and results-driven CIO / Director / Leader with a successful background in professional, education, financial services, manufacturing and corporate sectors. Commercially-aware and business-driven, with a broad range of experience having worked for world-class organisations including Nottingham Trent University, Logicalis, Goldsmiths & HBOS.

Strategic approach to successful leadership, engaging with key business stakeholders and 3rd parties, delivering 'cost appropriate' solutions and business process change in a variety of sectors and situations.

Experience of business change management, business transformation, service transition, strategy development and implementation, technology roadmaps, stabilisation of services, infrastructure renewal, shared service facilities, IT centralisation & systems integration, delivering added business value & ROI through the use of technology.

Specialties: it strategy, procurement, portfolio management, strategic planning, benefits realisation, budgeting, business process management, systems integration, contract management, crm, customer relations, customer service, data management, project delivery, application development, disaster recovery planning, acquisition due diligence, e - commerce, eai, ebusiness, general management, information security, information systems

Experience

Chief Information Officer at Goldsmiths, University of London

August 2014 - Present (2 years 8 months)

Responsible for defining the IT strategy and implementing improvements in information technology and information services within a world renowned creative university. Also leading improvements in business continuity.

- Reporting to Registrar and Secretary
- Identified immediate service issues and enacted a plan to deliver improved stability and customer experience
- Defined and agreed long-term strategic vision and plan which is now being implemented

Non Executive Director at Corporate Health

May 2013 - November 2014 (1 year 7 months)

Corporate Health is an occupational health charity founded in 1947, before the NHS was set up. As an appointed Non Executive Board Director I work with fellow directors and the executive team to give independent leadership and strategic direction.

Corporate Health works with businesses to optimise workforce attendance through looking after employee health and well-being. The charity covers the three main areas of occupational health, namely legislative, reactive and proactive. It focuses on delivering a high quality service, and its innovative approach means it offers clear, decisive, get-off-the fence commercially focused advice.

CIO at London South Bank University

August 2012 - July 2014 (2 years)

Providing leadership to the Information Communication Technology (ICT) department, developing and delivering ICT Strategic and Operational Objectives in support of the University's Business Plan.

Services Director at Logicalis UK

June 2011 - June 2012 (1 year 1 month)

Responsible for driving the delivery of improved revenues & profits through improved service delivery

- Appointed to strategic role within an international provider of integrated ICT solutions and technologies
- Focused on leading a programme of strategic change within the services organisation, improving profits
- Definition & execution of a revised strategy to transition IT infrastructure towards IT service management
- P&L business management responsibilities, driving in excess of £70m revenue & £17.5m gross margin
- Reporting directly to the Managing Director, advising on service delivery, technology and ICT solutions
- Leadership, management & motivation of a multi-functional team of 250+ staff, including staff coaching
- Conducted regular and in-depth evaluation of new IT technologies, maintaining competitive business edge
- Delivered key elements of business & IT strategies, providing annual savings of £475k+ & boosting profits
- Established relationships with key suppliers, leveraging vendor capabilities & delivering value for money IT

Director of Information Systems at Nottingham Trent University

November 2006 - July 2011 (4 years 9 months)

Responsible for ICT operations, IM strategy & information security within a leading UK-based university

- Appointed to spearhead continual improvement of communication within the Information Systems function
- Focused on stabilising the provision of information & communication technology-based services to users
- Director of a shared service company, delivering 2nd line support for Microsoft products in education
- Identified and negotiated an alternative supplier for call escalation, reducing costs by over £40k per year
- Director of EMMAN Ltd, delivering a Wide Area Network solution to 8 universities, plus schools & colleges
- Championed the delivery of enhanced information systems via a newly centralised, shared services team

- Delivered a new procurement strategy for IT saving £2.4m+ and underpinning roll-out of sector-leading IT
- Drove transition from a technology-led approach to a service-oriented solution, improving satisfaction levels

Head of Business Integration and Information Technology at HBOS plc

September 2005 - November 2006 (1 year 3 months)

Member of the Executive Committee of HBOS Europe Financial Services, with a team of 138 people and a budget of £16m; accountable for the IT operations, IT development, business operating model, IT strategy and IT governance for HBOS Europe Financial Services operation in Maastricht, Luxembourg, Milan, Vienna, Hamburg and Heidelberg.

Head of IT International at HBOS plc

November 2003 - September 2005 (1 year 11 months)

Reporting to the IT and Strategy Director of HBOS Financial Services with a team of 80 people and a budget of £10m; accountable for IT operations, project delivery, IT strategy, and disaster recovery.

Director of 6 HBOS Isle of Man companies and 1 Luxembourg company.

Head of IS CMI Financial Management Services Limited at HBOS plc

November 2001 - November 2003 (2 years 1 month)

Reporting to the Managing Director of CMI, and to the HBOS Financial Services General Manager for IT and Business Integration in a dual reporting role with a team of 62 people and a budget of £7m, accountable for the IT operations, project delivery, office services, disaster recovery, business continuity planning and the Isle of Man office facilities.

Director of six HBOS Isle of Man Companies.

IT Manager at Software AG (UK) Ltd

January 1999 - October 2001 (2 years 10 months)

Seconded to the Finance Director with a team of 6 and a budget of £750k, accountable for revitalizing internal IT and quality systems to maximise business effectiveness and profitability.

Led a team from demoralised under performance to delivering 100% of projects to budget and deadline. Successes include:

SAP Contract Management module implemented plus Vantive Customer Relationship Management system for Sales and Marketing

Senior Business Consultant at Software AG (UK) Ltd

January 1996 - January 1998 (2 years 1 month)

Reporting to the Professional Services Director, managed virtual teams of up to 15, accountable for specifying and delivering blue chip corporate client projects to budget and plan and directing programmes of work on client projects.

Business Manager at Software (AG) Ltd

January 1995 - January 1996 (1 year 1 month)

Re-engineering Services

Reporting to Professional Services Director, created a new worldwide re-engineering service " centre of excellence" for Software AG with a team of 10. Successes included:

Managed 12 client conversion projects valued at £500k+, securing account continuity, and achieved profit in year 1.

Established ISO9001 certified operating procedures.

Selected and supported international preferred partner portfolio to deliver client projects.

Business Manager at Professional Services

January 1994 - January 1995 (1 year 1 month)

Reporting to the Professional Services Director, had P & Director, L responsibility for the £3.13m Professional Services business unit. Successes included:

Achieved £903k gross profit.

Orchestrated (up to 4) concurrent projects (to £500k each) through project managers to deliver on time and budget.

Created ISO 9001 TickIT compliant standards and procedures including adapted PRINCE methodology and RAD.

Project Manager at Software AG (UK) Ltd

January 1992 - January 1994 (2 years 1 month)

Reporting to the Professional Services Business Manager, managing teams of 2-15 developers to deliver 7 projects (£5k - £425k) to budget and deadline. These included; Housing Benefits Application.

Enabled RBKC to overcome backlog of benefit claims and win the tender for the provision services when the situation became competitive.

OTIS Sales and Technical drawing application.

Automated the sales process and interfaced directly with AutoCAD to produce architects drawings.

Nissan Warranty Processing System.

Enabled Nissan to cost, track and measure all warranty claims and to run any major re-call initiatives.

Software AG Social Services package (SSIS) in conjunction with RBKC.

Managed development and subsequently took on product management role and assisted in sales to local authorities.

Nominated " Employee of the Quarter " for managing projects using a Rapid Application Development methodology. Software AG guaranteed to develop applications in half the time taken using conventional tools and methods.

Project Leader at Software AG (UK) Ltd

January 1987 - January 1992 (5 years 1 month)

Projects

Exceptional Student Experience

May 2014 to Present

Members: David Swayne, Professor Phil Cardew, Mike Watson, Laurence May, Cailean Carvalho

Project sponsor for a major initiative, working in partnership with IBM, which will focus on enhancing student engagement within the University (on top of hardware and software development focused on cloud servers and identity and access management).

Key strands of development include:

An integrated student portal, bringing together all systems (email, VLE, library systems, social networking, identity management) in one space for all our students.

Development of a 'master data management' approach to information held across multiple systems (student records, finance, fees, accommodation, library, VLE) focusing on maintaining a 'golden record' for all students.

Development of virtual social networks enhanced by information tagging and working across students, staff, alumni and employers/placement providers.

Use of 'predictive analytics' to enable smarter use of historic performance and engagement data to help us understand 'danger signals' in student participation and respond to them more immediately. Historic data will inform patterns of behaviour so that we can anticipate problems and intervene before students get into a real mess.

This is an exciting project which will take a couple of years to fully develop but we are entering the pilot phases of some systems very shortly, with further development over 2014/15.

Publications

Times Higher Interview

THE March 19, 2014

Authors: David Swayne, Chris Parr

Podcast of interview

Skills & Expertise

IT Strategy

Project Delivery

Business Management

Disaster Recovery

Change Programmes

Business Change Management

Directors

Business Process Re-engineering

Business Continuity

Portfolio Management

IT Service Management

Enterprise IT Infrastructure

Financial Services

IT Procurement

Enterprise Architecture

P&L Budget Management

OPEX

capex

Customer-focused Service

CRM

Technology Evaluation

Risk Management

Service Delivery Management

Full project lifecycle experience

Stakeholder Management

3rd Party Partnerships

3rd Party Relationships

Data Management

IT Security Policies

IT Business Strategy

Management

Change Management

Information Management

IT Management

Project Management

ITIL

Governance

IT Operations

Leadership

Team Management

Security

Infrastructure

Professional Services

Strategy
Business Process
Integration
Business Transformation
Customer Relationship Management (CRM)

Education

Institute of Directors

Diploma, in Company Direction, 2006 - 2007

International Management Centres Association

Master of, Management, 2003 - 2005

De Montfort University

BSc (Hons), Computer Science, 1980 - 1984

Interests

Golf, long distance cycling, gardening and photography

Organizations

Institute of Directors

Royal Society for the encouragement of Arts, Manufactures and Commerce

April 2004 to Present

David Swayne

Chief Information Officer at Goldsmiths, University of London

d.swayne@btinternet.com



5 people have recommended David

"David's focus on strategic and operational service improvement to support a positive student experience is both proactive and highly responsive to emergent developments and priorities. David's approach to the student experience is received positively by both colleagues and students alike."

— Hazel Willis, worked directly with David at London South Bank University

"The private sector experience David brought from HBOS etc. clearly worked well for Nottingham Trent University - and also had a wider influence within the higher education sector - including in my case the process for delivering a major IT partnership and procurement that I led at Loughborough. David's advice was invaluable, his judgement sound, and his views always pertinent. Now that David has moved back to the private sector, to Logicalis, I trust he will keep in touch with the many good public sector friends he has made."

— Phil Richards, was with another company when working with David at Nottingham Trent University

"David has been a customer of mine for over eight years across two different companies. Not only does David understand how to drive IT to deliver for organisations, he has the ability to forge excellent longterm relationships with his suppliers. In this his ability is simply outstanding."

— **Roger Stocker**, was a consultant or contractor to David at HBOS plc

"David is a highly experienced and well respected leader. David has many core strengths but the area where I personally evidenced David's great insight was around his ability to tackle complex strategic change initiatives. David embraces change and rises to the challenge of solving the most significant strategic issues. I very much enjoyed my time working with David and benefited from his ability to clearly articulate the 'correct path'."

— **Stephen Brooks**, worked with David at HBOS plc

"I worked with David at Software AG and found David's comprehensive business and technical knowledge to be without exception, his ability to solve the most complex of problems was a tremendous help to me as a Project Manager. Since then I have worked with David on several assignments in his roles as the Head of IT

operations at HBOS and NTU and have been very impressed by his grasp of strategic issues and his ability to deliver results in complex business environments. David also has a very calm collected style and is a pleasure to work with."

— Mike Watson, worked directly with David at HBOS plc

Contact David on LinkedIn